Southern California Women for Understanding (SCWU) collection, 1975-1999
UCLA Library Special Collections
Southern California Women for Understanding (SCWU) collection
1975-1999
1851
UCLA Library Special Collections
10.5 linear ft. (14 boxes, 1 shoe box, and 1 oversize box)
The Southern California Women for Understanding Collection contains the operational records of Southern California Women for Understanding (SCWU), one of the earliest lesbian non-profit educational organizations in Los Angeles, California.
Southern California Women for Understanding.
Restrictions on Access
COLLECTION STORED OFF-SITE AT SRLF: Open for research. Advance notice required for access. Contact the UCLA Library Special Collections Reference Desk for paging information.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
COLLECTION CONTAINS DIGITAL MATERIALS: Special equipment or further processing may be required for viewing. To access digital materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
History
Southern California Women for Understanding (SCWU), an educational non-profit organization, formed in 1976 and dedicated itself to "enhancing the quality of life for [the lesbian] community and for lesbians nationwide, creative and positive exchange about homosexuality, [and] changing stereotypical images of lesbians." SCWU emerged in the midst of the civil rights, gay rights, and women's movements when many marginalized social groups organized en masse to demand recognition and rights. SCWU was one of the earliest known lesbian organizations. At its height, SCWU reached membership of 1,100 and in 1982, Lesbian News hailed it as the "largest lesbian support group in the country."
SCWU originated as a "support group" of the Whitman-Radclyffe Foundation (WRF), a San Francisco based gay rights organization that strove to educate the public on homosexuality. In 1976, Betty Berzon, one of the few female board members, invited twenty women to form the Southern California Women for Whitman-Radclyffe Foundation. After forming a steering committee and electing officers, the women planned a series of "Special Interest Raps" which would allow lesbian women to come together and informally discuss a variety of topics. Founder Betty Berzon led SCWU's first Special Interest Rap, "Disclosing Your Gayness to Family and Friends." Berzon was a licensed psychotherapist who was one of the first to work with gay and lesbian clients.
In 1978, SCWU and WRF mutually severed its ties as WRF decided to exclusively focus their efforts on itself as an alcoholism treatment center for the gay population in San Francisco. SCWU flourished and focused its efforts on educational and social events, fundraising, legislative lobbying, and fostering projects for the lesbian community (i.e. Connexxus/Centro de Mujeres). In addition to its grassroots efforts in building a social space for the lesbian community in Los Angeles, SCWU strove to work with high profile figures. In 1977, SCWU Chair, Myra Riddell, travels to the White House as part of the National Gay Task Force which was invited by Margaret "Midge" Costanza, Presidential Assistant for Public Liaison. Its annual Lesbian Rights Award Dinner would honor a lesbian woman whose work benefited lesbians on a large scale. Honorees include Del Martin and Phyllis Lyon (Daughters of Bilitis founders), Elsa Gidlow (poet), Dianne Abbit and Roberta Bennett (attorneys, founders of first Sexuality and Lesbian Task Forces of the Los Angeles National Organization of Women chapter), Virginia Uribe (Project 10 founders), Adrienne Rich (writer), Gloria Anzaldua (writer), Cherrie Moraga (writer), and Jackie Goldberg (Los Angeles City Councilmember).
Being an educational organization, SCWU hosted a variety of educational programs from informal "rap" groups, theater productions (Welcome to Our Lesbian World), and guest speakers. Additionally, SCWU's research committee designed and executed studies on Los Angeles lesbian lifestyles. In 1977, SCWU surveyed its membership via the "Personal Profile Questionnaires" with questions on family, religious, educational, professional, health background as well as experiences with social and employment discrimination. The committee received 1,000 responses; the results were published in the SCWU newsletter.
In addition to the projects planned and executed by the central organization, SCWU had numerous area chapters that would plan and execute their own projects and events tailored to its respective constituency. The majority of the area chapters were located in California – Long Beach/Orange County, San Gabriel Valley, Los Angeles/Valley, Inland Empire, Palm Springs and desert areas, San Diego, Santa Monica and nearby beach cities, Ventura, Santa Barbara and Santa Maria. The only out-of-state chapter was located in Wilmington, Delaware. According to the Board of Directors minutes, there was some discussion about contacting lesbian groups in the southwest but there is no indication that area chapters formed in said region.
As evidenced by expensive fundraising dinners and other events that often charged a cover fee, it is evident that SCWU catered to a membership that consisted primarily of professional, middle and upper-class women, the majority of whom were white. In response to criticisms of being elitist, the Board of Directors began an internal dialogue on diversity in 1989.
Chronology
May 15, 1976 Betty Berzon sends a letter to twenty women inviting them to her home to discuss the formation of a steering committee for the Whitman-Radclyffe Foundation.
June 4, 1976 Berzon and twelve women meet to discuss WRF and a women's group.
June 14, 1976 Seven women meet again to elect committee officers: Myra Riddell (Chairperson), Terry DeCresenzo (Vic-Chairperson), Sue Philbrick (Secretary), Karen Weiss (Treasurer), Betty Berzon (Ex-Officio, Liaison to the Board). Pat Berlly, Gloria Muetzel, Irene Robertson, Jane Patterson, and Barbara Colby comprised the remaining committee members.
July 25, 1976 First membership appeal meeting held and attended by fifty women.
October 8, 1976 SCW-WRF hosts first Special Interest Rap, "Disclosing Your Gayness to Family and Friends." Speaker is Betty Berzon, a licensed psychologist.
January 30, 1977 Pat Denslow presents new by-laws to SCW-WRF.
February 25, 1977 SCW-WRF hosts Jean O'Leary, ex-nun, Co-Executive Director of National Gay Task Force, and openly gay delegate to the Democratic National Convention as well as Grace Davis Montanez, Deputy Mayor of Los Angeles.
March 26, 1977 Myra Riddell travels to the White House as part of the National Gay Task Force invited by Margaret "Midge" Costanza (Presidential Assistant for Public Liaison).
Fall 1977 SCW/WRF sends out Personal Profile Questionnaires aimed to find out more about lesbians' social conditions in Los Angeles. Report of results published in March/April 1978 newsletter.
September 10, 1977 SCW/WRF members present a workshop on various lesbian issues at USC. Workshop features keynote speaker Olga Broumas, first openly gay woman to win the Yale Younger Poets Prize.
July/August 1978 SCW-WRF announces its disassociation from the WRF and become known as SCW.
August/September 1978 SCW starts hosting Receptions for Understanding in which members could informally meet with potential allies in the non-gay community. The first Reception on August 24 was covered by NBC News.
September/October 1978 SCW becomes Southern California Women for Understanding (SCWU).
December 4, 1978 Forty women meet in Long Beach to discuss the formation of a Southern Committee of the SCWU.
January 6, 1979 Judi Doyle is named Chair of the Southern Committee.
September 15, 1979 SCWU holds first Lesbian Rights Award Banquet and honors Del Martin and Pyllis Lyon, founders of first lesbian organization, Daughters of Bilitis.
October 19, 1979 The Ventura Committee hosts its first Special Interest Program, "Women and the Law."
January 10, 1980 The Advocate features Myra Riddell and SCWU in a two page spread.
March 7, 1980 The San Gabriel Valley Committee holds its first Special Interest Program, "Orientation Rap" and is attended by sixteen women. Ret informally acts as Chair.
March 31, 1980 SCWU open its first office on 13719 Ventura Avenue, Suite D in Sherman Oaks.
August 1980 SCWU Board of Directors announces its re-structuring due to the growth of the organization.
September 5, 1980 Fifty women meet to discuss the formation of a Los Angeles/Valley committee.
February 14, 1981 SCWU hosts a Weekend of Lesbian Culture which features the second Lesbian Rights Award Banquet and honors lesbian poet Elsa Gidlow.
February 26, 1981 SCWU is granted tax-exempt status as a non-profit organization.
August 22, 1981 SCWU receives the National Organization of Women's Alice Paul Certificate of Feminist Achievement for Advancement of Feminist Goals.
October 29, 1981 Los Angeles/Valley committee becomes the second official chapter of SCWU.
January 1982 Judi Doyle begins tenure as the second Chair of SCWU.
August 1982 SCWU moves into new office with ACLU Lesbian and Gay Rights Chapter at 633 Shatto Place in Los Angeles.
May 7, 1983 SCWU holds its third Lesbian Rights Award Banquet and honors attorney activists and couple Dianne Abbit and Roberta Bennett, founders of the first Sexuality and Lesbian Task Force of the Los Angeles chapter of N.O.W.
June 28, 1984 SCWU announces its endorsement of Connexxus/Centro de Mujeres, a woman's center for Los Angeles.
December 9, 1984 A group of women in San Diego host a social to attract potential members for a San Diego SCWU chapter.
February 1985 SCWU moves to its third office on 9054 Santa Monica Boulevard, Suite 103 in West Hollywood.
The Ventura committee officially gains chapter status.
April 1985 Beach Cities Committee forms and includes Malibu, Santa Monica, Venice, Culver City, Inglewood, Marina Del Rey, Playa Del Rey, El Segundo, Manhattan Beach, Hermosa Beach, Redondo Beach, Torrance, Palos Verdes and Rancho Palos Verdes.
June 1985 Jean Conger is appointed by the Board of Directors for the new position of Executive Director.
January 1986 Margo Strik begins tenure as the third Chair of SCWU.
January 18, 1986 SCWU holds its fourth Lesbian Rights Award Banquet and honors first Chair Myra Riddell.
September 1986 Inland Empire announced as a Formation Group.
February 1987 Beach Cities Steering Committee decides to disband due to lack of member participation.
March 7, 1987 SCWU holds its fifth Lesbian Rights Award Banquet and honors musicians Margie Adam, Meg Christian, Holly Near, Linda Tillery and Cris Williamson.
March 12, 1988 SCWU holds its sixth Lesbian Rights Award Banquet and honors lesbian comedian and activist, Robin Tyler.
July 24, 1988 Inland group gains chapter status.
January 1989 Cultural Diversity Task Force formed to facilitate discussion on cultural diversity and SCWU membership.
March 4, 1989 SCWU holds its seventh Lesbian Rights Award Banquet and honors Virginia Uribe, founder of Project 10.
August 31, 1989 Jean Conger resigns from Executive Director position.
March 17, 1990 SCWU holds its eighth Lesbian Rights Award Banquet and honors Karen Thompson, lesbian and human rights activist.
March 16, 1991 SCWU holds its ninth Lesbian Rights Award Banquet and honors lesbian writers May Sarton, Adrienne Rich, Rita Mae Brown, Charlotte Bunche, Katherine Forrest, Paula Gunn Allen, Gloria Anzaldua, and Cherrie Moraga.
July 7, 1991 SCWU sponsors the IMRU radio program on KPFK 90.7 with Theresa Erreca and Dr. Woolbridge.
July 28, 1991 A Wilmington, Delaware group and Desert Women's Association gain chapter status.
Board decides on the "dba" (doing business as) name of "National Association of Women for Understanding" to reflect the national nature of SCWU.
August 1991 Santa Barbara group holds preliminary meetings.
September 1, 1991 Santa Maria group holds first meeting.
November 3, 1991 Santa Barbara group gains chapter status.
March 14, 1992 SCWU holds its tenth Lesbian Rights Award Banquet and honors Roberta Achtenberg, Member of the Board of Supervisors for the City and County of San Francisco.
April 17, 1993 SCWU holds its eleventh Lesbian Rights Award Banquet and honors Colonel Margarethe Cammermeyer, Captain Dusty Pruitt, and attorney Mary Newcombe.
April 23, 1994 SCWU holds its twelfth Lesbian Rights Award Banquet and honors Jackie Goldberg, Los Angeles City Council Member.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 6650672
Related Material
This collection forms part of the The June L. Mazer Archive at UCLA.
See Connexxus/Centro de Mujeres Collection which originated as a project under the non-profit auspices of SCWU.
Southern California Women for Understanding.
Container List
- Board of directors., 1975-1993.; Series 1.; 87.0 folders
  Material relates to functions of the board such as policy making, meetings, and fundraising. Contains print materials (minutes, policy drafts, correspondence, newsletters, subject files) as well as audio cassettes and photographs.
  Arrangement note
  Sub-series are arranged in chronological order.
  - Founding papers., 1975-1986.; Subseries 1.; 5.0 folders
    Documents were originally contained in a three-ring-binder separated by dividers labeled by year. Each folder contains a divider section of the original binder.
    The "Founding Papers" sub-series encompasses the early documentation of SCWU when it was a "support group" of the Whitman-Radclyffe Foundation (WRF). Folders include notes and correspondence from founder Betty Berzon, WRF newsletters, SCW's correspondence with WRF and early correspondence with supporters and members. See folder scope/content notes for a more detailed inventory.
    - 1976., 1975-1986.; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Contains Betty Berzon's original invitational letter for the WRF women's "support group," sign-in sheet (with blank spaces left to preserve women's anonymity), timeline of WRF women's support group, correspondence regarding the internal conflict and future of WRF, WRF board and SCWU meeting minutes, WRF newsletter, Berzon's notes for educational programs and projects, SCW's proposal to the WRF board regarding their official relationship, and letters of endorsement, support and outrage to public officials and business and media executives. "Notes for Aron and Claudia re SCWU 'first documents' as BG to 10th anniv NL article SCWU NEWSLETTER" by Bunny MacCulloch (1986) details the origins of SCWU as a "support group" of the Whitman-Radclyffe Foundation (WRF) started by Betty Berzon. MacCulloch briefly outlines SCWU's initial challenges and learning process of working together, by-law and policy making, official severance from WRF, estrangement from original members Terry DeCrescenzo and Betty Berzon, and the resignation/firing of June Mazer as newsletter co-editor.
      Folder also contains famous "Closet ad" (1975) by WRF that appeared in major publications such as Times, Newsweek, Harpers, Wall Street Journal, The Atlantic, and The Advocate.
    - 1977., 1977-1978.; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Photocopied handwritten notes on steering committees' responsibilities and by-laws by Pat Denslow. SCW correspondence to the Los Angeles County Board of Supervisors and Margaret "Midge" Costanza at the White House. WRF newsletter (Winter/Spring 1977) detailing SCW/WRF members' "Ten Gays in the White House" trip and January 1978 issue. Minutes of WRF Board of Directors meeting (May 5, 1978)
    - 1978., 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Correspondence (handwritten and typed drafts) to members, WRF personnel, legislators, and SCW members from Dianne Crocker (Communications Secretary) and Myra Riddell (Chairperson). Memorandum and letters of resignation from WRF board members and WRF Board of Directors meeting agenda (July 6, 1978).
    - 1979., 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Correspondence regarding board members' resignations, member appreciation, organization endorsement. Recipients include members, National Organization for Women (NOW), ACLU, Del Martin and Phyllis Lyon (Daughters of Bilitis founders), from Myra Riddell (Chairperson), Bunny MacCulloch, June Mazer.
    - 1980., 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Correspondence with the IRS, ally organizations, thank you letters to presenters at Special Interest Programs (SIP), resigning board members, letters of acceptance to new board members, and memorandum by Bunny MacCulloch and Maribeth Kelly (Corresponding Secretary), Myra Riddell (Chairperson), and other board members.
  - By-laws, procedures, and structure., 1976-1989.; Subseries 2.; 26.0 folders
    Documents were originally contained in three-ring-binders separated by labeled dividers. The original order was maintained by labeling folders according to the dividers. The sub-series is arranged by a loose chronological order as there is some overlap on the years.
    Contains drafts and final versions of by-laws, procedures and organizational structure.
    - Board structure., 1976-1989.; 4 folders (Box 1, Folders 6 - 9)
      Folder 6: Member lists (1976-1989)
      Folder 7: Ballots and elections (1977-1993)
      Folder 8: Guidelines (1980-1986)
      Folder 9: Functions (1979-1984)
      General note
      Material was originally contained in a three-ring-binder entitled "Board structure." Folders have been divided and labeled according to the binder dividers.
    - By-laws and standing rules., 1977-1983.; 2 folders (Box 1, Folders 10 - 11)
      Folder 10: By-laws (1977-1983)
      Folder 11: Standing rules (1977)
      Material was originally contained in a three-ring-binder. Folders have been divided and labeled according to the binder dividers.
    - Procedures., 1979-1986.; 9 folders (Box 1, Folders 12 - 20)
      Folder 12: Review (1979)
      Folder 13: Procedures committee report (1980)
      Folder 14: Summaries (1982)
      Folder 15: Board of directors (1985)
      Folder 16: Financial (1985)
      Folder 17: Newsletter (1985)
      Folder 18: Committees (1985)
      Folder 19: Personnel, formation of chapters, miscellaneous (1985)
      Folder 20: General and board of directors procedures
      Material was originally contained in a three-ring binder entitled "Procedures." Folders have been divided and labeled according to the binder dividers. See also Box 2, Folders 31-35 for more procedures documents.
    - Organization re-structure of 1980., 1980-1982.; 4 folders (Boxes 1,15, Folders 21 - 24)
      Folder 21: Beginning the process (1980)
      Folder 22: Retreat reading materials (1980)
      Folder 23: Retreat (1980)
      Folder 24: Results (1981-1982)
      BOX 15
      One audio cassette labeled "June 6th SCWU 1981."
    - Five year plan., 1982-1985.; 7 folders (Box 1, Folders 25 - 31)
      Folder 25: Directions (1982)
      Folder 26: Retreat (1983)
      Folder 27: Follow-up (1983)
      Folder 28: Consolidation (1983)
      Folder 29: Consolidation (1984)
      Folder 30: Membership interaction (1984)
      Folder 31: Second decade plan for progress (1985)
      Materials originally contained in three-ring binder labeled "5 Year Goals." Folders have been divided and labeled according to the binder dividers.
    - Elections., 1984-1994.; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Minutes, correspondence., 1976-1993.; Subseries 3.; 23.0 folders
    Minutes are arranged in chronological order by year.
    Minutes are from Board of Directors and Executive Committee meetings. Contains two audio cassettes of the January 23, 1983 board meeting.
    - Minutes (Board of Directors and Executive Committee)., 1976-1993.; 18 folders (Boxes 1 - 2, 15, Folders 32 - 41, 1 - 8)
      BOX 1
      Folder 32: June, August-December (1976)
      Folder 33: January-October, December (1977)
      Folder 34: January-December (1978)
      Folder 35: January-December (1979)
      Folder 36: January-December (1980)
      Folder 37: January-December (1981)
      Folder 38: January-December (1982)
      Folder 39: January-October, December (1983)
      Folder 40: January-November (1984)
      Folder 41: January-December (1985)
      BOX 2
      Folder 1: January-December (1986)
      Folder 2: January-August (1987)
      Folder 3: February, December (1988)
      Folder 4: January, March-April, June-August, November-December (1989)
      Folder 5: January-September (1990)
      Folder 6: January, March-August, November (1991)
      Folder 7: January (1992)
      Folder 8: June (1993)
      Contains two audio cassettes labeled "Board brainstorm Jan 23 1983."
    - Correspondence., 1986.; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Judi Doyle papers., 1978-1987.; Subseries 4.; 33.0 folders
    The papers were originally contained in a box labeled "Judi Doyle papers to break down and put in notebooks" and were not arranged in any particular order. Instead of integrating the documents into the rest of the collection, the processor decided to keep them separate as they reflected the breadth of responsibilities and activities in which Doyle was involved as a chapter founder, board member, and SCWU chair. The organizational schema of her papers roughly mirror the arrangement of the Central administrative files with folders in alphabetical order by subject.
    Judi Doyle was one of the founders of the SCWU Southern chapter and later served as Chairperson and board member of SCWU. Her papers relate to various aspects of her tenure in leadership positions at SCWU. This sub-series also contains three photographs.
    - Award, Vicky Awards Committee., 1980.; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 9)
      Certificate of Nomination for Supporting Organization (1980) presented to SCWU by Vicky Awards Committee
    - Circular letters., 1986-1987.; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Circular letters from gay and lesbian focused and/or friendly organizations, including SCWU.
    - Clippings., 1982-1986.; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 11)
      Two copies of clippings from The News featuring a letter to the editor from June Mazer.
    - Committees., 1982-1985.; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 12)
      Documents produced by the Central Communications, Education, Membership and Research Committees as well as proposals for committee structure.
    - Connexxus., 1985.; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence., 1980-1986.; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Events., 1979-1985.; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Financial records., 1982-1987.; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Forms., undated.; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Founding papers., 1978.; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Handbook., 1983.; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Insurance., undated.; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Meetings., 1979-1984.; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Miscellaneous documents., 1982.; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 22)
      Maps, directions, and information on the Woman's Building in downtown Los Angeles.
    - Newsletter., 1979-1987.; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 23)
      Includes handwritten drafts of newsletter copy by Judi Doyle.
    - Personnel., 1980-1985.; 5 folders (Box 2, Folders 24 - 28)
      Folder 24: Applicants (1980-1985)
      Folder 25: Forms and procedures (1980-1982)
      Folder 26: Executive Director applicants (1985)
      Folder 27: Fundraising Chair applicants (1982)
      Folder 28: Managing Editor applicants (1985)
    - Nominations for the Board., 1986.; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Photographs., 1984.; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 30)
      Three 5x7 black and white photographs. No people are identified. One is labeled "Board doing newsletter assembly (1984)."
    - Procedures., 1980-1987.; 5 folders (Box 2, Folders 31 - 35)
      Folder 31: 1980-1984
      Folder 32: 1985
      Folder 33: 1986
      Folder 34: 1987
      Folder 35: undated
      See also Box 1, Folders 12-20 for more procedures documents.
    - Proposals to the board., 1985-1988.; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Rosters, board members., 1980-1984.; 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 37)